A Guide to the John Steinbeck Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6239-b
John Steinbeck Collection 1934-1962
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6239-b
18 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase
Item Listing
- Manuscript
  - Scene from Of Mice and Men, [ca. 1939]; AM, 3 p.
    [Includes note in hand of [ Eugene Solow] "added scene for picture version of
    Of Mice and Men
    -cut out of picture."]
- Letters
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1949 Aug 18]; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses returning the boys [ John Steinbeck IV and Thom Steinbeck] to Gwyndolyn Conger \Steinbeck,
    The Wayward Bus
    [a screenplay]; briefly discusses
    Cup of Gold
    mentions A. L. [ Annie Laurel Williams], Solow's man [ Charles Feldman], New York City, Florida, Sanchez, and
    characters Van Brunt, [Ernest] Horton, Johnny/Juan Chicoy, Pimples [Ed "Kit" Carson], [Elliot] Pritchard and Mrs. P [Bernice Pritchard].]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1949] Oct 11; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses "this tie" [to Elaine Anderson Scott], the picture [
    ], [Elia] Kazan and
    Viva Zapata!
    , a pen; mentions E. [ Elaine Anderson Scott], Russ.]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1949 Dec 30]; ALS, 1 p. w/env (Penciled notes on envelope)
    [Discusses Solow's ailment, the script [
    ], moving and starting the play [
    Burning Bright
    ]; mentions [ Charles Feldman], Jack [Wagner], Rio, A. L. W. [ Annie Laurie Williams], Elaine Anderson Scott, and the kids [ John Steinbeck IV and Thom Steinbeck].]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950] Jan 25; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses life with Elaine Anderson Scott; briefly discusses weather, the play [
    ], the picture [
    ], a planned trip to Sweden with the boys [ John Steinbeck IV and Thom Steinbeck], and
    As You Like It
    mentions Stockholm, [
    The New York] Times
    ,
    , [
    New York Herald] Tribune
    , and California. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950 Feb 8]; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses [Charles] Feldman's business dealings regarding the [screen] play [
    ], the play [
    ] and plans to work with Gadg [Elia Kazan] and [Darryl Francis] Zanuck on
    briefly discusses Solow's spirit taking a beating, the relationship between Zachary Scott and Shelley Winters and Annie Laurie [Williams] plans to talk to Feldman; mentions The Viking Press, Mexico, New Orleans, and Elaine Anderson Scott. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950 Feb 20]Monday; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses as trip to work with [Darryl Francis] Zanuck on
    , a possible conference with him, [Charles] Feldman, and [ Jack Wagner and Max] Wagner; mentions Annie Laurel [Williams], Beverly HIlls Hotel, and Rio. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950 Mar 29]Wednesday; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses the picture [
    ], the purchase of his play [
    ] by [Richard] Rodgers and [Oscar] Hammerstein [II], work with [Elia] Kazan on
    , Elaine Anderson Scott having the flu, going to
    The Wisteria Trees
    , rain making, "red hunts", and Solow's town as "a sink-hole of sex"; mentions [ Charles Feldman].]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950 Apr 10]Monday; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses love, cancellation of a trip to Sweden, and Annie Laurel [Williams]; briefly discusses the play [
    ], Elaine Anderson Scott and work with Gadg [Elia Kazan] on
    mentions the kids [ John Steinbeck IV and Thom Steinbeck], [
    ], Texas and Scandinavia. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950] Aug 15; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses the play [
    ],
    , the stage version of
    Cannery Row
    , someone [ Gwyndolyn Conger Steinbeck] who made "a fool of herself"; briefly discusses Solow being "drowned in spit," Jerry Wald, [Humphrey] Bogart, "
    Nothing So Monstrous
    " from
    The Pastures of Heaven
    as film material, his long novel
    East of Eden
    and Elaine Anderson Scott; mentions Jules Buck, [ Twentieth Century] Fox, Annie Laurie [Williams], Boston, New Haven, New York City. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950] Aug 22; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses [
    ] script; mentions [Charles] Feldman. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950] Sep 14; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses Solow's need to "get out of there," the play [
    ], Elaine Anderson Scott, the boys [ John Steinbeck IV and Thom Steinbeck], and weather [in New York City]; briefly discusses [Jo] Mielziner, moving back to town and Annie Laurie [Williams]; mentions Gwyndolyn Conger Steinbeck, [Guthrie] McClintic, New Haven, Boston, and The Feldman Festival. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950 Oct 20]Friday; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses how "the critics murdered us" [regarding the play
    ] and its effect upon him; briefly discusses the play's chances in Europe and [Robert] Garland's notice.]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950] Nov 2; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses weathering the killing of the play [
    ], starting his long novel [
    ], the book [
    ], plans to marry Elaine Anderson Scott, [Jack] Wagner and Max Wagner; mentions New York City. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1950 ca. Nov 5]; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Discusses Annie Laurie [Williams] handling "the business in hand," Solow's girlfriends, buying a house, The Wayward [movie], [ Humphrey Bogart], plans to marry Elaine Anderson Scott; briefly discusses
    [the play and the book], and article ["Critics, Critics Burning Bright] which he wrote for
    Saturday Review of Literature
    , Betty, the phone strike, [Elia] Kazan's problems with
    A Streetcar Named Desire
    , a trip [to Bermuda], Jules Buck, starting his long novel [
    ], Solow and Joan Crawford as sponsors of his relationship with Elaine, attending the ballet [by Le Grand Ballet du Marquis] de Cuevas, seeing Gadg [Elia Kazan], weather; mentions Harold [Kleinert] Guinzberg, New York City, Broadway, Denmark and Vienna; two notes to John Steinbeck and Elaine Anderson Scott, are on the back of the envelope in [ Eugene Solow's ] hand.]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Eugene Solow], [1951] Jan 27; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses a new house, a trip, the
    script, [ Louella Parsons], and work on his new book [
    ].]
  - John Steinbeck to [Eugene] Solow, [1954] Feb 10; APCS
    [Discusses a film Solow is doing and giving him more stories, a trip to Spain, plans to see the other two films and "a new deal" involving narration on John Steinbeck's part; mentions Europe. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Eugene Solow, 1962 Nov 9; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses Jack Wagner and Author's Playhouse, Inc.; mentions Charlie and New York City. ]